Finding Aid for James K. Pollock Papers, 1920-1968
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- University of Michigan 1924-1967, 3.7 linear foot
  - Political Science Course Materials
    - Arranged by Course Number
      - 130 -- National Administration
        - Pre-1940, 2 folders (Box 75)
      - 140 -- Comparative European Governments: Lecture notes circa 1962-1966 (Box 75)
        see also P.S. 52, 350 and 741
      - 150 -- German Government: Outlines and study questions Undated (Box 75)
        see also P.S. 441
      - 198 -- Political Psychology: Notes, Articles and Papers 1935, 2 folders (Box 75)
      - 201 -- Scope and Method of Political Science, n.d (Box 75)
      - 210 -- National Politics
        - Lecture notes and outlines 1965, 2 folders (Box 75)
        - Topics, quizzes 1954, 1964 (Box 75)
      - 213 -- Seminar: Notes and Papers 1941, 2 folders (Box 75)
      - 216 -- Proseminar in Political Behavior 1949 (Box 75)
      - 251 -- British Government: Miscellaneous Undated, 3 folders (Box 75)
      - 252 -- Comparative Governments
        - Notes, n.d (Box 76)
        - Notes and outlines 1957-1961 (Box 76)
        - Notes and reading lists 1961, 1964 (Box 76)
        - Outlines and bibliography of minor governments 1958-1959 (Box 76)
      - 314 -- Comparative European Electoral Systems: Bibliography, Notes and Papers 1956, 3 folders (Box 76)
      - 350 -- Comparative European Governments 1955 (Box 76)
        see also P.S. 52, 140 and 741
      - 371 -- Seminar: Notes, Exams, Schedule, Bibliography Undated, 2 folders (Box 76)
      - 441 -- German Government
        see also P.S. 150
        - Bibliography, n.d (Box 76)
        - Class folder Undated, 2 folders (Box 76)
        - Notes and miscellaneous, n.d (Box 76)
        - Outlines and exams Undated, 2 folders (Box 76)
        - Research reports, n.d (Box 76)
      - 741 -- Comparative European Governments: Bibliography, Notes and Exams 1961, 1964 (Box 76)
        see also P.S. 52, 140 and 350
    - Arranged by Topic
      - Comparative Government Test File (sample) Undated (Box 76)
      - Comparative Studies in Public Administration 1936 (Box 76)
      - Congress Undated (Box 76)
      - Constitution Amending Process circa 1924-1939 (Box 76)
      - Constitutional Law Undated (Box 76)
      - County Government Undated (Box 76)
      - Courts-Judicial Reorganization and Review Undated (Box 76)
      - Czechoslovakia -- Course Miscellaneous Undated (Box 76)
      - European Politics and Electoral Systems -- Comparative Party Politics -- Germany Undated (Box 76)
      - France -- Course Miscellaneous (Box 76)
      - German Elections 1930 (Box 76)
      - German Government
        - Background and Analysis (Box 76)
        - Cabinet -- Parliamentary Leaders (Box 77)
        - Field Survey of the 1953 Bundestag Elections, 1953 (Box 77)
        - Foreign Policy Undated (Box 77)
        - German Parties and Elections Undated (Box 77)
        - Nazi Period Undated (Box 77)
        - Notes on Pre-Nazi and Transitional Period Undated (Box 77)
        - Personal Reports on Germany Undated (Box 77)
        - Personnel Undated (Box 77)
        - World War II and Occupation Undated (Box 77)
      - German Trip 1934 (Box 77)
      - Germany -- Leading Books, Quotations, Personal Views, Bruning Letters Undated, 2 folders (Box 77)
      - Great Britain Politics and Government
        - Administration -- Civil Service Undated (Box 77)
        - Cabinet and Cabinet System Undated, 2 folders (Box 77)
        - Constitution -- Monarchy Undated (Box 77)
        - Local Government Undated (Box 77)
        - Parliament Undated (Box 77)
        - Parties and Elections Undated (Box 77)
      - Immigration, Finance, Commerce Undated (Box 77)
      - Initiative, Referendum and Recall Undated (Box 77)
      - International Politics -- League of Nations Undated (Box 77)
      - Judge Advocate General School Lecture on Germany 1943 (Box 77)
      - Lecture Notes on Germany -- Fort Custer Lectures 1943 (Box 77)
      - Lobbying Undated (Box 77)
      - Michigan Commission on Reform and Modernization of Government (Hayden Commission) 1938 (Box 77)
      - Miscellaneous Course Exams, Outlines, etc. circa 1950-1967 (Box 77)
      - Miscellaneous Speeches, Lectures, Seminars, etc. 1943-1963 (Box 77)
      - Miscellaneous Information on Germany for Lectures to Specialty Group Meetings 1941-1945 (Box 77)
      - Naturalization 1924 (Box 77)
      - Nominating Systems, Conventions, Primary, Presidential, Defects of Present Electoral System 1945 (Box 77)
      - "Other Side of Judicial Review, The" Undated (Box 77)
      - Political Parties Seminar -- Notes, Bibliography, Topics Undated (Box 77)
      - Political Theory Undated (Box 77)
      - Presidency pre-1945 (Box 77)
      - Proseminar on Germany 1944 (Box 77)
      - Soviet Union -- Course Miscellaneous Undated (Box 77)
      - Suffrage, Elections, Voting Statistics pre-1940 (Box 77)
      - Territories circa 1924-1939 (Box 77)
- Speeches and writings 1920s-1968, 5 linear feet
  Speeches and Writings (5 linear ft.; 1920s-1968) covers all of Pollock's professional interests but is especially strong on German history, politics, and government. The speeches are arranged by date (when known) or by topic if that was a file heading used by Pollock. The speeches subseries also contains transcripts of Pollock's radio addresses. The articles subseries is arranged by date or subject. Also included with this series are Pollock's file of article reprints and copies of books that he wrote or co-authored.
  - Speeches
    - By date
      - Undated, 1920s-1930s (Box 78)
      - 1921-1931 (Box 78)
      - 1932-1936 (Box 78)
      - 1937-1938 (Box 78)
      - 1940s-1960s, undated (Box 78)
      - 1939-1941 (Box 78)
      - 1942-1945 (Box 78)
      - 1946-1949 (Box 78)
      - 1950-1954 (Box 78)
      - 1955-1960 (Box 78)
      - 1962-1968 (Box 78)
    - Radio speeches
      - 1928-1934 (Box 78)
      - 1940-1942 (Box 78)
      - 1942-1943 (Box 78)
    - By topic
      - Berlin speeches (Box 78)
      - Education and schools (Box 78)
      - Foreign affairs/foreign policy material (Box 78)
      - Foreign relations. Conduct of foreign relations material 1951-1963 (Box 78)
      - German topics
        - General, 2 folders (Box 78)
        - Post-1945 (Box 78)
        - "Germany-Keystone of European Peace" (Box 78)
        - "Report from Germany" and related (Box 78)
        - "Aspects of the Occupation of Germany" 1946 (Box 78)
      - Intergovernmental relations 1967 (Box 79)
      - International organizations (Box 79)
      - Michigan constitutional revision speeches 1942, 1963 (Box 79)
      - Politics and elections 1938-1944 (Box 79)
      - Russia (Box 79)
      - World War and post-war issues 1942, undated (Box 79)
    - Special Occasion
      - Alumni University and Extension Service presentations (Box 79)
      - Notes for James K. Pollock presidential address at the International Political Science Association meeting in Rome 1958 (Box 79)
      - Speech: "Forum for Press" (re constitutional revision in Wisconsin) May 17, 1965 (Box 79)
      - Limitation of Armaments Conference
        - 1925 (Box 79)
        - 1926, 2 folders (Box 79)
    - Anecdotes and quotations to be used in speeches (sample)
      - Undated (Box 79)
  - Articles
    - By date
      - 1920s, 2 folders (Box 79)
      - 1928-1930 (Box 79)
      - 1931-1934 (Box 79)
      - 1935-1937 (Box 79)
      - 1937-1938 (Box 79)
      - 1939-1944 (Box 79)
      - Manuscripts (various), 6 folders (Box 79)
    - Book reviews (Box 79)
    - By topic
      - Quay, Matthew. Essay for the Dictionary of American Biography on Matthew Stanley Quay-manuscript and background information, 1926-1931 (Box 79)
      - Political Science Department (U-M). Brochure written for the 50th anniversary of the Political Science Dept. of the University of Michigan 1960 (Box 79)
  - Reprints of articles
    - 1925-1926 (Box 80)
    - 1927-1929 (Box 80)
    - 1930-1934 (Box 80)
    - 1935-1939 (Box 80)
    - 1940-1941, 2 folders (Box 80)
    - 1942-1944 (Box 80)
    - 1945-1950 (Box 80)
    - 1951-1958 (Box 80)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 80)
    - 1962-1967 (Box 80)
    - Undated (Box 80)
  - Books written or co-authored by James K. Pollock
    - On Germany and German government (Box 81)
      (includes some reviews of books)
    - On American government; Michigan government; and other (Box 82)
- Clippings 1924-1968, 1 linear feet
  Clippings (1 linear ft.; 1924-1968) covers the span of Pollock's career. The clippings were for the most part commercially prepared. The researcher should note the existence of clippings in other parts of the collection as indicated.
  - 1924-1938 (Box 83)
  - 1924-1941 (Box 83)
  - 1941-1943 (Box 83)
  - 1944-1948 (Box 83)
  - 1949 (Box 83)
  - 1950 (Box 83)
  - 1951 (Box 83)
  - 1952 (Box 83)
  - 1953-1955 (Box 83)
  - September 1952-September 1959 (Box 83)
  - September 1959-September 1965 (Box 83)
  - September 1965-September 1966 (Box 83)
  - September 1966-September 1968 (Box 83)
  - Civil Service reform in Michigan 1936-1937 (Box 83)
  - Undated (Box 83)
  - General, 6 folders (Box 83)
- Visual Materials 1920s-1960s, 1 linear feet
  The Visual Materials (1 linear ft.; ca. 1920s-1960s) series includes both photographs and motion pictures.
  - Photographs
    The photograph subseries consists of portraits, photos of Pollock with other individuals, attending professional meetings, speaking or receiving awards. A large portion of this subseries are photos of Pollock, his staff, and other high officials in the military government and the German Länderrat. Included is an album of photographs documenting Pollock's receipt of the Grand Cross Order of Merit in 1956 from the president of the German Federal Republic, Theodor Heuss.
    - James K. Pollock portraits
      - Formal portraits (Box 84)
      - Informal and James K. Pollock as youth (Box 84)
    - With Konrad Adenauer (Box 84)
    - With various dignitaries (Box 84)
    - James K. Pollock speaking (Box 84)
    - James K. Pollock as part of larger groups (Box 84)
    - James K. Pollock receiving miscellaneous awards (Box 84)
    - James K. Pollock receiving the Grand Cross of the Order of Merit from the German Government 1956, 2 volumes; 1 folders (Box 84)
    - James K. Pollock travels (Box 84)
    - James K. Pollock attending professional meetings (Box 84)
    - James K. Pollock as part of U-M Dept. of Political Science, ca. 1930 (Box 84)
    - James K. Pollock as part of Michigan civil service and other study groups 1930s (Box 84)
    - James K. Pollock as delegate to Michigan Constitutional Convention (Box 84)
    - Office of the Military Government for the United States 1946-1947
      - General, 4 folders (Box 84)
      - James K. Pollock's staff and villa where they worked (Box 84)
      - Memorial book with photos and text concerning the Länderrat meeting March 5, 1946 (Box 84)
      - German officials (Box 84)
      - German buildings and views (Box 84)
      - Postcard views of Germany (Box 84)
    - German travels 1948
      - American Zone (Box 84)
      - British Zone (Box 84)
      - French Zone (Box 84)
      - Unidentified (Box 84)
    - Portraits of others inscribed to Pollock (Box 84)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 84)
  - Motion Pictures
    - 1930s visit to Germany-Prewar Germany, circa 1934
      The Vereinigung Carl Schurz presents "Germany 1934" directed by O. V. Bothmer. A pictorial record of the "Carl Schurz Tour" of American professors and students through Germany in the summer of 1934. The tour was designed to further "the friendly relations between America and Germany on the basis of mutual understanding and goodwill."
      - Part 1 "Germany 1934" [8635-1-1]
        Part I of the film includes footage of the trip on the liner "Bremen" to Bremen; View of Berlin and Potsdam; East Prussia: Danzig, (Anthushop, St. Mary, Townhall, Frauengrasse, Krontor), Zoppot, Gdinia, Marienburg Castle; Marienwerder Finkenstein Castle, Tannenberg monument to Hindenberg; Kant grave; Rauscen on the Baltic; Dresden-Zwinger, Weimar-Schillerhau; Goethe's Garden House, Nietzsche Archives; Goethe House; Adolf Hitler passing through Weimar in a car; Jena, Nüremberg Nazi Party parade.
        - Original:, 16mm film, b/w, pos, optical, 00:31:40
          [Restricted]
        - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 5)
        - Streaming File: 8635-1-1, flv
      - Part 2 "Germany 1934" [8635-1-2]
        Part II of the film includes footage of the trip from Rothenburg to Augsburg; Ammersee, Oberammergau, Scenes from Passion Play; Ettal Church; Munich, German National Museum; Heidelberg Castle, Speier Cathedral; Saarbrücken, Trier, Rhein, Bonn; Beethoven Museum Cologne-Cathedral; Hamburg Tiederhaus (modern architecture).
        - Original:, 16mm film, b/w, pos, optical, ca. 00:35:0
        - Videotape, 3/4-inch tape (Box 85)
          (Includes both reels (Part I and Part II) of film. Dubbed from film by Allied Film in 1991)
        - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 5)
          (This DVD h includes both part 1 and part 2 and was created by Michigan Productions from 3/4-inch tape, not as part of the preservation project)
    - Die Partie Hat Immer Recht" circa 1953 [8635-2-2], [possibly East German, or West German reediting of East German propaganda film]
      - Original:, 16mm film, b/w, pos, optical, 00:51:36
      - Videotape, 3/4-inch tape (Box 5)
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 5)
    - "Interview:" Konrad Adenauer, ca. 1953, 1 optical disks 10 minutes; DVDs (Box 85)
      The Adenauer interview covers a range of topics including discussions of the destruction of 1945; reconstruction of Germany; Russian army occupation; warning of world communism; friendship with France; return of prisoners from Russia; and a contrast of East and West German prosperity.
    - "Ein Mann wirbt fur sein Volk" [Adenauer tour of U.S.] circa 1954, 1 optical disks 25 minutes; DVDs (Box 85)
      Visit of Adenauer to the United States during Conant period
    - "Adenauer und seine Mannschaft" [CDU election film] circa 1957, 1 optical disks 20 minutes; DVDs
      The film titled "Adenauer und seine Mannschaft" includes election speeches by party functionaries; Adenauer speech on Germany's position in the world; speeches by various state governors (Länder presidenden) and presentation of political figures including Kurt Kiesinger, Heinrich Lübke, Ludwig Erhard and Gerhard Schröder.
      - Election speeches of party functionaries (Box 85)
    - "Keine Experimente" circa 1960, 1 optical disks 5 minutes; DVDs (Box 85)
      (animated CDU election film on Konrad Adenauer's leadership on the topic of NATO)
  - Cartoons
    - Concerning Michigan civil service and Frank Murphy drawn by Frank Williams for Detroit News (?), ca., 1936 (Box 85)
      [Stored in oversize folder, Ac Pollock]
    - "Adenauer und seine Mannschaft" ca. 1957, 1 optical disks 20 minutes; DVDs
      [CDU election film]
      - Election speeches of party functionaries; Adenauer speech on Germany's position in the world; speeches by various state governors (Länder presidenden) and presentation of political figures including Kurt Kiesinger, Heinrich Lübke, Ludwig Erhard and Gerhard Schröder (Box 85)
    - "Keine Experimente" ca. 1960 (animated CDU election film on Konrad Adenauer's leadership on the topic of NATO), 1 optical disks 5 minutes; DVDs (Box 85)
- Sound Recordings, 1949-1963, 1 linear feet
  The Sound Recordings (1 linear ft.; 1949-1963) series consists of reel-to-reel tapes of Pollock lectures and addresses, and sound disks of an appearance on CBS News (probably discussing the Hoover Commission).
  - Sound tapes
    [Digitized audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.]
    - Symposium: Political Science 52: The East-West Conflict, 1950, 2 Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
      - [Tape 1, Part 1], [8635-SR-1-1]; mp3 file; (A debate centering around the differences between Western societies and Communist societies.)
      - [Tape 2, Part 1], [8635-SR-2-1]; mp3 file; (A debate centering around the differences between Western societies and Communist societies.)
    - Symposium: Political Science 52: Federalism, 1950, 2 Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
      - [Tape 1, Part 1], [8635-SR-3-1]; mp3 file; (Discussion of several governmental systems in North America and Europe.)
      - [Tape 1, Part 1], [8635-SR-4-1]; mp3 file; (Discussion of several governmental systems in North America and Europe.)
    - Symposium: Political Science 52: Parliamentary vs. Presidential Government, 1950 March 07, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
      - [Tape 1, Part 1], [8635-SR-5-1]; mp3 file; (Tape content does not match original description; recording discusses Catholic Parochial schools in Flint, Michigan.)
      - [Tape 1, Part 2], [8635-SR-5-2]; mp3 file; (Tape content does not match original description; a brief 38 second recording of a discussion about Walt Whitman.)
    - Symposium: Political Science 52: Parliamentary vs. Presidential Government, 1950 March 07, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
      - [Tape 1 Part 1], [8635-SR-6-1]; mp3 file; (Discussion and debate on the differences between Parliamentary and Presidential governments.)
    - Symposium: Political Science 52: Parliamentary Democracy in Post War [Europe], 1950, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
      - [Tape 1, Part 1], [8635-SR-7-1]; mp3 file; (Discussion and debate about issues of parliamentary democracy in post-war Europe.)
      - [Tape 2, Part 1], [8635-SR-8-1]; mp3 file; (Discussion and debate about issues of parliamentary democracy in post-war Europe.)
    - Lecture: Post War Trends in Executive Power, 1950 January 10, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
      - [Tape 1, Part 1], [8635-SR-9-1]; mp3 file; (Pollock discusses the executive branches in North America and Western Europe in the Post-War era. There are no interviews on this tape.)
      - [Tape 2, Part 1], [8635-SR-10-1]; mp3 file; (Pollock discusses the executive branches in North America and Western Europe in the Post-War era. Interviews with three West German Bundestag members begin at 17:40.)
    - Lecture: Post-war trends in party alignments, 1950 January 17, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
      - [Tape 1, Part 1], [8635-SR-11-1]; mp3 file; (Pollock lectures on power and party dynamics in Post-War Western Europe.)
      - [Tape 2, Part 1], [8635-SR-12-1]; mp3 file; (Pollock lectures on power and party dynamics in Post-War Western Europe.)
    - Lecture given in Munich, 1953 August 29, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 10.5 inch, 15
      - [Part 1], [8635-SR-13-1]; mp3 file; (Pollock discusses the progress of post-War Munich, Germany, and German reunification. Answers prewritten questions throughout the tape.)
    - Address of Wilhelm Grewe, German ambassador to the United States entitled "Germany facing the Summit", 1959 December 09, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
      - [Part 1], [8635-SR-14-1]; mp3 file; (No content for first five minutes. Speech centers on German, European, and American relations and Summit Meetings. Address also includes citation for decoration given to James K. Pollock.)
    - Debate in Grand Rapids, Michigan, between James K. Pollock and [Harold Norris] over ratification of the Michigan constitution, 1963 January 04, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 3.75
      - [Part 1], [8635-SR-15-1]; mp3 file; (Debate betweeem Pollock and Harold Norris includes topics of Bill of Rights, limitations of current Constitution, and implications of new Constitution.)
  - Sound discs and wire recording
    - Address to Pacific Southwest Academy on the work of the Hoover Commission July 1949, 1 wire recordings (Box 86)
    - Townhall address in Los Angeles, Calif. June 20, 1949, 1 wire recordings (Box 86)
    - CBS News November 24-25, 1949, 4 phonograph records 16" (Box 86)
    - Second National Reorganization Conference of the Citizens Committee for the Hoover Report, 2 phonograph records 16" (Box 86)
- Personal/Miscellaneous 1919-circa 1960s, 2 linear feet
  The Personal/Miscellaneous (2 linear ft.; 1919-ca. 1960s) series consists of a subseries of personal correspondence covering the period from July 1945 to August 1946, when Pollock served as special adviser to General Lucius D. Clay, deputy governor of the American zone. The letters are written by Pollock to his wife, Agnes, and occasionally to his mother and sister, first from Berlin (location of the Central Control Council, a joint council made up of the military leaders of the four occupying powers) and later from Stuttgart (where the RGCO was located, and where the Länderrat met). The letters supplement Pollock's occupation diary for this period (found in Box 58) by providing a more personal perspective on his activities. They contain summaries of and observations about Pollock's work for the American Military Government, descriptions of the places he visited, and information about the practicalities of daily life and his feelings about being away from his family. There is also correspondence from Pollock's later visits to Germany in 1947 and 1948. The letters from his 1947 visit (Jan.-March) are particularly valuable because no occupation diary exists from this period. A folder of miscellaneous correspondence contains some letters from 1941, plus some written during later visits to Germany in 1950 and 1956. The scarcity of letters during these later trips is explained by the death of Pollock`s wife in October 1948.
  This series also contains a miscellanea of personal materials, programs from public appearances, address books, presentation copies of some of the books given to Pollock throughout his career, and some of the student essays that he wrote while a student at Harvard and the University of Michigan. Included as well is a transcript of the oral history interview with Pollock conducted by Sidney Fine and relating to civil service reform in Michigan and Pollock's relationship to Governor Frank Murphy.
  - Personal correspondence to wife and other family members
    - June-July 1945 (Box 87)
    - August 1945 (Box 87)
    - September 1945 (Box 87)
    - October 1945 (Box 87)
    - November 1945 (Box 87)
    - December 1945 (Box 87)
    - January 1946 (Box 87)
    - February 1946 (Box 87)
    - March 1946 (Box 87)
    - April 1946 (Box 87)
    - May 1946 (Box 87)
    - June 1946 (Box 87)
    - July 1946 (Box 87)
    - August 1946 (Box 87)
    - January 1947 (Box 87)
    - February 1947 (Box 87)
    - March 1947 (Box 87)
    - May 15-July 2, 1948 (Box 87)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence 1941-1956 (Box 87)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Anderson, Dennis. Draft of James Kerr Pollock bulletin (Box 87)
    - Awards, certificates, letters of appreciation, 4 folders (Box 87)
      [also oversize folder Ac Pollock]
    - Address books, 1 folders (Box 87)
    - Biographical material (Box 87)
    - Christmas and other cards from various dignitaries (Box 87)
    - Oral history transcript conducted by Sidney Fine with James K. Pollock relating to civil service reform in Michigan and to the gubernatorial administration of Frank Murphy (Box 87)
    - Presentation copies of books signed by authors or with inscriptions from other dignitaries, 4 volumes (Box 87)
    - Programs, 5 folders (Box 88)
    - Travel files
      - Europe 1955 (Box 88)
      - Egypt 1962 (Box 88)
    - University of Michigan/Harvard student materials
      - History thesis: "Anglo American Relations" 1919 (Box 88)
      - Debating materials 1920, 2 folders (Box 88)
      - Essay: "The Colombian Treaty" 1921 (Box 88)
      - Essay: "Bolingbroke and Burke on Party" (Harvard University) (Box 88)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 88)